<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The complaint of a Christian soule Containing certaine remedies and comforts against the trouble and conflict of conscience. Newlie written in meter.</title>
            <author>Muschet, George, poet.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119581</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854788</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854788</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20232</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20232)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1211:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The complaint of a Christian soule Containing certaine remedies and comforts against the trouble and conflict of conscience. Newlie written in meter.</title>
                  <author>Muschet, George, poet.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Charters [sic], printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.X. [1610]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: George Muschet.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:2"/>
            <p>THE COMPLAINT OF A CHRISTIAN SOVLE.</p>
            <p>Containing certaine remedies and comforts <hi>againſt the trouble and conflict of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newlie written in meter.</p>
            <p>PRINTED AT EDINBVRGH BY RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Charters, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie. M.D.C.X.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:3"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST NOBLE AND HIS ſingulare good Lord IOHN Earle of MONTROSE Lord Grahame, one of his Majeſties privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, we wiſhe long life with increſſe of <hi>honour in the feare of the Lord</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthogh, moſt Noble Lord, I (as one ever mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of your L. honorable place, and of that dewtie we all ought therevnto) did not lacke a will to haue ſaluted your L. with ſome fruites of my travelles this long time ago: but finding in my ſelfe that great want of graces which my Muſe ſhould haue granted, and not being bould to haue preſented my ſelfe emptie into your preſence, as alſo fearing if I had offered anie thing that my barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and incongruous ſpeech ſhould rather haue moued your L. to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like me for my homelines, then otherwiſe to haue receiued me in fauour for the ſame. Yet being long tosted betwixt two extremities, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times calling to minde the dewty I was bound to, and ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering how I was alwaies vnable (becauſe of my manifold defects) to haue ſatiſfied the leaſt point of your worthie deſire, haue in end thoght better to be rude then vngrate, and ſo much the more becauſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the theam propoſed vnto me, I must with your favour (althogh not with ſuch learning as you merite, nor with ſuch holines as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requyres) take the boldnes as to acquaint your L. mith my ſmall beginning, and to ſpeeke a little of this ſubiect concerning a troubled ſoule, and of the comforts againſt the conflict of conſcience, as a thing preſcrived vnto me for the tyme, being in the ſame agonie my ſelfe (for my owne priuate content, and to avoide the tediouſnes of ill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed tyme) I was perſwaded by ſome who had a great intereſt to the diſpoſition of my will, to publiſh this little ſcrole to the world, that others might reape ſome profite thereby, and be fortified againſt the feare and apprehenſion of the gilt of ſinne, and certainly the worthines of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect mooued me to yeeld the more eaſily to their deſires. Yet knowing that students in their beginning (how worthie ſo ever) haue but a cold
<pb facs="tcp:20232:4"/>welcome in a forren land without the ſupport and countenance of ſome great &amp; worthie perſonage, as alſo fearing my imperfections, in handling this ſukiect, might happely blemiſh the excellency of the worke, and giue ſome dstiaſte to the curious reader. I haue therefore in my boldnes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected it to your L. as a patron, hoping ye will rather be a <hi>preſes</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my weaknes, then to cavell or oppon againſt ſuch tender propoſitions. For ſince all that I haue done, rather proceedes of loue and bounden dewry, then any ſantaſticall toy or deſire of renoun: I muſt therefore commit all my ſlips and ignorances to your L. ſubſidie, looking rather to be acceptable for my good will, then to be loathed for that quhilk is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laiking in me, and thought vnſavorie for that quhilk in due affection is done. So I haue preſumed to ſhrewd both my ſelfe and my labours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your L. protection, beſceching you receaue theſe strangers (as you vſually do all men) with a gratious and a gentle eie, and to accept of my poore endevours, as a testimonie and a pledge of my humble dewty and ſervice: that by your L. honourable acceptance and exemple, others may be drawne to entertaine them kindely, and bid them the better welcome: ſo ſhall your L, incourage me to ſome ſtronger attempt, and bind me to continew alwaies, promiſing certemly if mymuſe ſhall afford any better things thereafter, neither ſhall your perſon nor your place be forge, but as my taient increſſes your L.ſhall know.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>MY greateſt reverence is not halfe my dew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For more nor all my worth thy worth requyres:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By my attempt I wiſhe there might enſew</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But ſome contentment to thy hie deſires:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And as before the Sun no darknes bides,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Sunnie cies my imperfections hides.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue quhilk dwels into the inward thoght,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Makes good the ſeed what ever be the ſmell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The outwarde gloſſe ſome time doth ſeeme but noght,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quhill as the inward ſtuffe doeth much excell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gold thogh not finde ſome men do well eſteeme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I rather loue to be then ſo to ſeeme.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble oratour in Chriſt M. <hi>George Muſchet.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a great happines to fle al vicious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, and to hold a commend able medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocritie: ſo it is a miſerie quhilk we cannot ſufficiently lament, to ſee (in thir latter daies amongſt men quhilk make profeſſion to beleeue in a better life) ſome who haue ſo ſold them ſelfe to the loue of this world that they ſeeke not for an vther, and ſome who are ſo violently caried away with the feare and apprehenſion of Death, ſo that vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhew of alteration in their health there is nothing to be heard bot ſtrange ſighs and grones, the witneſſes of abject thoghts, and the vnworthie conteſting of a ſoule that wolde diſpute with God. The remedies againſt ſo great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieues are very neceſſary: and I hope this treatiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will furniſh ſome-what for the purpoſe (gathered not in the bogs and mures of humane wiſdome, but in the garden of life) quhilk is the Scriptures of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of the ever-living God: The ſavory juce of the quhilk remedies digeſted in our ſoules, will make vs neither be too much rejoiſd with the pleaſures of this world, neither too much feard to paſſe out of this world, but that with a holy care, a vigilant feare, and a filiall reverence, we ſhall haue the eies of our ſoules and eares of our heartes open to the voice of the Lord, crying to all mankinde, <hi>Sonnes of men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> yea it wolde cure vs of that lethargie, palſie, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall apoplexie, where-with ſo many poore ſoules are daily infected, quhilk never thinking of death are dead li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or rather are as the dead quhilk bury the dead, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing
<pb facs="tcp:20232:5"/>what the kingdome of God is, neither hauing any care to be of it, or to procure or advance it. This juce will free vs from that feare quhilk congeils our ſpirits, and from that frencie quhilk makes vs doubt of our ſaife delivery, and from that ſpirituall melancholy quhilk ſubverts all true judgement in vs, and thruſts vs (as it were) in a brutiſhe childiſhnes, eſtranging vs from theſe things quhilk ſhould cauſe moſt joy and conſolation in vs. This preſent collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the box conteining the precious oyle the quhilk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carefully digeſted by you will (I hope) produce ſome profitable effect. Bot to giue you ſome greater taiſt of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, and to ſhew the ſumme or this little ſcrole. In thir few &amp; vnadviſed lynes, there is breeflie (or as it wer) in a certaine a bridgment ſet down two things, the one is the vehement calamitie quhilk proceedes not from a ſleeping ſoule, but from the feeling diſeaſe and exceſſiue trouble of a wakned conſcience, not onely accuſed but convicted of her perſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and broght to the ſtraite , farther nor the ſcaffold, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven almoſt to the doore of the graue, by the rememberance of ſin. In the other part there is adjoind, althogh not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately by it ſelfe but mixtly throgh the whole, ſome ſpeciall remedies for the moſt diſeaſed ſoule, and ſome medicens equivalent for the farreſt dijected conſcience, and ſome ſalues very neceſſarie for that ſpirituail palſie, quhilk if it be rightly applyed, will not onely baniſh all preſent feare of death, but even that quhilk no other Phiſick can afford, it will furniſhe perpetuall health to the ſoule, and leaue the minde ſo at eaſe, that no inconvenient (how great ſo ever) ſhall be able heereafter to ty the man to the bed. This is the ſumme Chriſtian Reader, and albeit it be not ſo ripely dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, nor vttered with ſuch grace, as he ought to haue who lets any thing go from him to the cenſure of this age: yet impudencie hes ſo prevailde with me for the time, and a care to do good with my ſmall talent, did ſo continually puſh
<pb facs="tcp:20232:5"/>my lukles muſe that I could finde no reſt in ſilence. But as Michall did laugh when David did dance, ſo I know ſome Michals will ſcorne at my ſinging, and yet I hope other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be welcomed of ſome, for if any good Davids be in this land there I ſhall be harbored, becauſe this is a ſong whereat Davids ſhould be delyted. So not caring for Michals taunting, nor Rabſchek as railings, nor Iſchmaels ſcofs, becauſe it is not with ſuch I craue to be mirrie, neither with them to communicate our ſpirituall melodie, to the well effected Chriſtian (who giues lodging to the Hebrew Harpes, and who intertaines the muſicall inſtruments of Sion) I direct this Ballad, to be ſet vpon their ſtrings, to be played in their Palaces, and to be ſung in their Innes, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this one that if the pleaſantnes do not delite you, the long ſomnes ſhall not wearie you. And if all be not ſo well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as you merite (worthie Reader) nor ſo Poeticallie compoſed as the writer wolde wiſhe, let my want be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervailed by my good will, and when better things ſhall be offered, you ſhall not lacke.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fair well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:6"/>
            <head>THE COMPLAINT OF A CHRISTIAN SOVLE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Oulde God I had ſuch acceſſe to thy face,</l>
               <l>As of before when I thy favour fande:</l>
               <l>Would God my ſoule were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with grace,</l>
               <l>That I might liue as thy worde doth command.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhould my life for ever preach thy praiſe,</l>
               <l>My lippes ſhould found thy mercies manifold:</l>
               <l>Much ſhould I ſcorne for to be one of theſe,</l>
               <l>Whom Sathan ſin death, hell or worldlings wold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ah, my wittes can not ſo far aſpyre,</l>
               <l>My ſenſleſſe heart is ever hardened ſo:</l>
               <l>That while thy ſpirit in me ſhould haue impyre,</l>
               <l>Sin raignes to death,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> that all my weils doe go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ere I liue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I rather chuſe to die,</l>
               <l>And die I dare not for my great treſpaſſe:</l>
               <l>Except in death thy ſonne ſhould pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e me,</l>
               <l>And waſh my ſoule while it be cleane as glaſſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:7"/>
               <l>Sinnes great deceate vnto the world is knowne</l>
               <l>By olde experience and by practiſe late:</l>
               <l>And I poore wretch am daylie overthrowne,</l>
               <l>And ſpoilde by ſinnes which conſcience doth repeate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her glittring ſhades and her allurements ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Moude me to yeelde, and did me captiue take:</l>
               <l>And therefore iuſtlie may the Lord revenge,</l>
               <l>To my great greefe and everlaſting wracke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My great offences if I ſhould expreſſe,</l>
               <l>I know large ſcrolles could not the ſame contene:</l>
               <l>And neither are my privie falts the leſſe,</l>
               <l>But much more frequent in my life hes bene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My falſe affection and my corrupt will</l>
               <l>Hath ſold my ſoule to everie ſort of ſinne:</l>
               <l>And this fraile fleſh conſpyring ay my ill</l>
               <l>Lettes ſuithing fancies all my freedome win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus can I never to the heavens approch,</l>
               <l>So much infect with everie blemiſh thing:</l>
               <l>No, no, I haue not boldnes in ſo much,</l>
               <l>Once to beholde thy countenance bening.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For oh, the vylenes of my great treſpas</l>
               <l>Wrappes me in chaines of darke eternall cair:</l>
               <l>And I forgot how ſweete thy preſence was,</l>
               <l>My lights are darke, my eyes ſees life na mair.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo it skilles not what my ſinnes haue beene,</l>
               <l>I ceaſe t'abridge, much more to finde them out:</l>
               <l>For if my leſſer faultines were ſeene,</l>
               <l>I ſhould be odious all the world throughout.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:7"/>
               <l>Therefore with David I mon rather wine</l>
               <l>My ſinnes were covered and my ſlippes forget,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.</note>
               </l>
               <l>That my perverſnes and my deeds amiſſe</l>
               <l>Quench not the courage that ſhould mercie get.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For if thy goodnes doe deny releefe,</l>
               <l>Falne are my hopes like widdring leafes to ground:</l>
               <l>None can expreſſe the agonie and greefe,</l>
               <l>Which in my conſcience daylie does abound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For oh, my ſinnes vnto the heavens are gone</l>
               <l>My ſoule to baniſh from that pleaſant place,</l>
               <l>Yea, that quhilks more my life is almoſt done,</l>
               <l>And wrakt by that perturber of my peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thogh this be much it is not all my we,</l>
               <l>But heere the greefs quhilk doe me moſt annoy,</l>
               <l>That I remember how my God was ſo,</l>
               <l>My light, my loue, my life, my hope, my joy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to haue ſind againſt ſo fair a face,</l>
               <l>O it wolde cruſhe a world of ſoules in care,</l>
               <l>And I who liud in ſin ſo long a ſpace,</l>
               <l>Except thou help muſt die into diſpare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thogh my lukles life hes ay bene ſuch,</l>
               <l>As did tranſgres the limits of thy law,</l>
               <l>Yet my offences are not halfe ſo much,</l>
               <l>But to thy ſervant thou may mercy ſhew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For nons caſt off but ſuch as haits thy Name,</l>
               <l>And none do periſh but who dies perverſe,</l>
               <l>None dies to torment but who liues in ſhame,</l>
               <l>Bad life brings death, and does all joys diſperſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:8"/>
               <l>Such am I not, with all my ſtrength I loue thee,</l>
               <l>And my perverſnes I ſinceerely hate:</l>
               <l>I loath my ſinfull life, and longs to prooue thee</l>
               <l>Sweete, kinde and gratious to my poore eſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My ſinnes are great, but heere my comforts haill,</l>
               <l>Thou knowſt that which I would not, that I do:</l>
               <l>And yet not I, but my corruptions faill,</l>
               <l>And thus I'am ſinfull all the worlde vnto.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But oh, my ſpirit doth ſorrow for my ſin,</l>
               <l>Althogh my fragile fleſh be frighted ſo:</l>
               <l>My ſoule doth long to ſee the dayes begin,</l>
               <l>That my affection from the world ſhould go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iude</note>My former walking I abhorre ſo much,</l>
               <l>The coat thats ſpotted with the fleſh I hate:</l>
               <l>Yea I diſdaine the members made me ſuch,</l>
               <l>And loathes my ſelfe that I was ſo ingrate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thogh I doe bewaile my ſinnes eachone,</l>
               <l>And all my crooked wayes with teares lament:</l>
               <l>And thogh I ſmart for that great evill thats done,</l>
               <l>While I ſinceerely for my ſinnes repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet am I ever troubled and diſmaide,</l>
               <l>Becauſe my God hath hid his gracious face:</l>
               <l>Sathan rejoices that I am affraide,</l>
               <l>And willes me never looke for anie grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus am I humbled, but too much caſt downe,</l>
               <l>And ſees my ſinnes, but in a fearefull glaſſe:</l>
               <l>This ſight willes meto th'vncouth land be bowne,</l>
               <l>And ſuch ſtrong charge doth all my ſtrength ſurpaſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:8"/>
               <l>Doth thus my God conſpire my woe and wrack<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Or did he not a gracious faviour ſend?</l>
               <l>Or doth he onelie life from me abſtract?</l>
               <l>Or ſhall I yet haue happines in end?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy ſtrength is not diminiſhed, I know,</l>
               <l>Thy arme not ſhortened to thine owne elect:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 8.</note>They taſte of Sions fontaine ſweete Siloa,</l>
               <l>And drinks the brock which from the river breek.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 21.</note>Thou giues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> food which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doth raine</l>
               <l>Thou'le quench their thirſt even w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the water of life:</l>
               <l>Once let me drinke, that I thirſt not againe,</l>
               <l>And finiſh quicklie all my woe and ſtrife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For thou delights not in a ſinners death.</l>
               <l>And haſt no pleaſure wounded ſoules to kill:</l>
               <l>No, thou canſt not rejoice to ſtop the breath,</l>
               <l>Thogh we be frighted with a world of ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The dame would not ſo gladlie keepe her yong,</l>
               <l>For all the flightring of her feathers faire:</l>
               <l>The mothers hand is not ſo ſoftlie hung,</l>
               <l>To ſaue her childe of whom ſhe hes great caire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As thou haſt thine out-ſtretched armes abrod</l>
               <l>For their deliverie who regardes thy name:</l>
               <l>No, thou art theirs, and they are thine, ô God,</l>
               <l>And ſo, thogh loſt, yet thou canſt bring them hame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then this that I doe ever ſo bewaile,</l>
               <l>Is not becauſe with thee their is no grace:</l>
               <l>No, no, it's rather that I am ſo fraile,</l>
               <l>And hes not eyes to ſee thy gracious face,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:9"/>
               <l>For what great comfort can thy grace afford?</l>
               <l>Or what a joy is it thy mercie brings?</l>
               <l>Or what a pleaſure is thy glorie, Lord?</l>
               <l>If thou with-hold from me theſe precious things.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, it doth ſeme but to aggredge my paine,</l>
               <l>To ſee ſuch plentie and ſo ſmall to teaſt:</l>
               <l>I rather wiſh my lights were darke againe,</l>
               <l>Or by ſuch ſight my life were ſo oppreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But let my faith go apprehend thy loue.</l>
               <l>And make my hope aſſured of thy joyes:</l>
               <l>And let my thirſtie ſoule theſe mercies proue,</l>
               <l>Iſe loath the worlde and all her fooliſh toyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhall I not vnto my fancie liue,</l>
               <l>Nor worldlings beſt contentments longer loue</l>
               <l>Th'earths fading glorie I ſhould not archieue,</l>
               <l>But ever long eternitie to prooue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eſter 3.</note>Hamans preferment I ſhould not reſpect,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Luk, 16.</note>All Dives riches ſhould not once content met</l>
               <l>I Alexanders kingdomes ſhould reject,</l>
               <l>And not rejoice thogh all the world were lent me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But all my thoghts outthrogh the clouds ſhold reik</l>
               <l>My words aboue the higheſt mountaines roare:</l>
               <l>And my delights ſhould be of heaven to ſpeik,</l>
               <l>My joy to thinke on that eternall glore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſince my faith is ever weakened ſo,</l>
               <l>And all my hopes are ſhadowed with care:</l>
               <l>And ſince thy quickning ſprite departs me fro,</l>
               <l>That living I among the graues repaire,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:9"/>
               <l>How can my thoghts or words to heaven aſcend?</l>
               <l>How can my deing ſprites exalt on hie?</l>
               <l>How can my courage in ſuch woe be kend,</l>
               <l>While it is loadned in perplexitie?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My life is death if ſo I liue alaſſe,</l>
               <l>My courage faintnes, all my pleaſure paine:</l>
               <l>My reſt is tedious, all my health diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Except ſome comfort from the heaven doe raine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know thy goodnes may aſſwadge my ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Thogh I encounter with theſe perrelles all:</l>
               <l>Thy ſacred Booke ſhowes thou maieſt ſaue my life,</l>
               <l>And keepe it harmeles both from death and hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Exod 14</note>For Iſraell ſcapt from that Egyptian hoſt,</l>
               <l>And eke againſt proud Pharao ſo prevailde:</l>
               <l>That horſſes, chariots, Capitaines he loſt,</l>
               <l>The rotten reede of Egypt ſo him failde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1. Kin. 19</note>That ſtrong Aſſyrian armie was defeate</l>
               <l>By heavenlie powers of their liues bereft:</l>
               <l>And Sions Cittie ſaued from perelles great,</l>
               <l>And Aſhur ſlaughtered when the ſeege he left.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Young David with the Philiſtim did fight</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam 19</note>By that great ſtrength of God and not of man:</l>
               <l>Saules beſt coat-armour could not fit him right,</l>
               <l>By other forces he the battell wan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Pharo, Aſhur and Goliah ſtrong</l>
               <l>Shall take the foile, if yet thy ſtrength thou grant me</l>
               <l>And I triumph thy holie Courts among,</l>
               <l>And be victorious when the world ſhall want me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:10"/>
               <l>My paines may ceaſe, my trouble ſhall depart,</l>
               <l>And all my inward greefes ſhall haue an end:</l>
               <l>And I haue ſolace yet for all my ſmart,</l>
               <l>If thou ſhalt mercie to thy ſervant ſend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No foraine forces, no domeſtick fo,</l>
               <l>Shall once aſtoniſh or amaze my minde:</l>
               <l>Except my haynous treacherie doe go,</l>
               <l>And make my Saviour to my ſoule vnkinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note>I know my ſinnes may make me loſe thy loue,</l>
               <l>Loyttring in Sodome may procure thy hate:</l>
               <l>Or to looke backe when from the world I moue,</l>
               <l>May ſerue to metamorphoſe my eſtate,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Num, 11.</note>Or to loath Manna and that heavenlie fude,</l>
               <l>And long for Egypts fatnes in the plaine:</l>
               <l>May make the firie ſerpents be too rude,</l>
               <l>And ſting to death, that we liue not againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Ionas 1.</note>Or to repyne againſt thy holie will,</l>
               <l>And go to Tharſis that ſhould Nineue teach:</l>
               <l>May toſt the ſillie ſhip with ſtormes ſo ſhill,</l>
               <l>And caſt poore Ionah in a fearefull ditch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In Sodome, Egypt, Tharſis, noght but woe,</l>
               <l>Althogh their dainties doe a while delight thee:</l>
               <l>Their pleaſures periſh, all their games do go,</l>
               <l>And ſorrowing ſadnes ſhall in end requite thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, noght in earth but croſt delights is ſeene,</l>
               <l>And all her ſweetnes mixt with bitter gall:</l>
               <l>For where to day triumph and ball hes been,</l>
               <l>To morrow mourning oftentimes befall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:10"/>
               <l>What ſhall I then ſuch bad contentments loue?</l>
               <l>Which noght but momentaneall comfort brings:</l>
               <l>No, no, my ſoule delights to be aboue,</l>
               <l>To ſee the valour of eternall things.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where there is endles happines of life,</l>
               <l>And perfect pleaſure for the Saints preparde:</l>
               <l>Glorie but ſhame and reſt withoutten ſtrife,</l>
               <l>As hes the holie Scriptures oft declarde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then theſe great things ſhould everie fancie wiſſe,</l>
               <l>For this abiding wealth the world ſhould cair:</l>
               <l>For it brings life and ſuch perpetuall bliſſe,</l>
               <l>That Abrahams children needs to wiſh na mair.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which if my ſoule were once ſure to injoy,</l>
               <l>When all this vaile of miſerie is paſt:</l>
               <l>No earthlie conſlict heere ſhould me annoy,</l>
               <l>Becauſe I ſhould poſſeſſe the heavens at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But all toyle, troubles, contrare change of time,</l>
               <l>My faith ſhould welcome, and not be affraide:</l>
               <l>Thogh cares would blaſt the bloſſomes of my prime,</l>
               <l>That I were fynde or as in morter brayde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All ſhould I embrace as tokens of thy loue,</l>
               <l>And I ſhould feed vpon thy favour ſtill:</l>
               <l>My ſongs of praiſe ſhould mount to heavens aboue,</l>
               <l>While I were faſhioned to thine holie will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhould I alwaies ſolemnize thy name,</l>
               <l>For this deliverie to thy ſervant granted:</l>
               <l>To ſing thy mercie this ſhould be my theame,</l>
               <l>As did the godlie who thy Courts hes hanted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:11"/>
               <l>On Davids Harpe oft ſhould my finger ſtrike,</l>
               <l>Yea Davids heart in my breaſt ſhould be found:</l>
               <l>That heavenlie voice which from my lippes ſhold brek</l>
               <l>Moſt Echo-like among the rocks ſhould ſound,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No muſick ſhould but Hebrue ſongs delight me,</l>
               <l>Thogh all the Muſes with their mirth were broght:</l>
               <l>I know the lecherous ſinger will deſpight me,</l>
               <l>But all his ſonnets ſhould I ſet at noght.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good Ezechias to thy houſe ſhould lead me,</l>
               <l>With David to the Temple ſhould I paſſe:</l>
               <l>And holie Moſes throgh the Courts ſhould guide me,</l>
               <l>In Sions ſongs ſhould be our merineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But who can ſing in ſuch a monſtrous graue?</l>
               <l>Or praiſe thy name in this infernall place:</l>
               <l>Who can be glade who doth nor grace receaue</l>
               <l>To ſee the ſweemes of thy heavenlie face?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or can his voice be heard in heavens aboue,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſoule is cruſhed in the earth below?</l>
               <l>Or may my minde be warmed with thy loue,</l>
               <l>While ever frowning thou thy ſelfe doeſt ſhow?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh raiſe my ſoule from ſuch a gulffe of care,</l>
               <l>As thou didſt Lazarus bodie from the graue:</l>
               <l>Reviue my ſpirits that yet I may repare</l>
               <l>Theſe pleaſant places which the Saints receaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For oh, thou ſeeſt my fainting in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>How no mans torment is ſo much as mine:</l>
               <l>And how my paines are ſo remedileſſe,</l>
               <l>That thogh I liue, yet in that life I pine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:11"/>
               <l>Muſt this, alaſſe, thy ſervant needs be gone?</l>
               <l>That all ſupporting ayde is from him raine:</l>
               <l>Or ſhall I die before my dayes be done?</l>
               <l>Or ſhall I liue when all theſe dayes are gane?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If once thy former mercie was ſo great,</l>
               <l>When as thou ſparedſt all the world for one:</l>
               <l>One may haue acceſſe to thy mercies ſeat,</l>
               <l>Throgh all in all who ſits vpon the Throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For once he ſuffered for my great treſpas,</l>
               <l>Once he was offered for the ſinnes of men:</l>
               <l>In him thy verie juſtice pleaſed was,</l>
               <l>Of force thy mercie muſt remit vs then.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So all my troubles and afflictions ſtrange</l>
               <l>Shall not deſtroy me nor procure my wrack:</l>
               <l>Becauſe my God he doth not ſtill revenge,</l>
               <l>But tryes his children when he does them ſtrike.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The mother doth abſent her ſelfe a while,</l>
               <l>From her deare childe whom ſhe intierly loueth:</l>
               <l>And ſo the infant after this exile,</l>
               <l>In his affection much more fervent proueth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So thogh my God from me his face obſcure,</l>
               <l>Yet will he kyith when all theſe clouds are paſt:</l>
               <l>And this diſertion ſhall my ſoule allure,</l>
               <l>To loue more trewlie not I loued laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Its not to leaue me that my God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Its not to kill me that he ſends the croſſe:</l>
               <l>He doth not ſtrike that I ſhould die anone,</l>
               <l>But fines the gold by burning of the droſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:20232:12"/>
               <l>Since by the fornace our corruption dies,</l>
               <l>And all our faultie parts are framde of new:</l>
               <l>And all the trouble that the bodie ſees,</l>
               <l>Serues but to make it of an heavenlie hew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We ſhould not fret to be afflicted much,</l>
               <l>Since by afflictions we the heaven attaine,</l>
               <l>And none to Canaan ever can approch,</l>
               <l>But he who in the wildernes hes bene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then thogh great waters do ſo oft beſet mee,</l>
               <l>That Sathan ſays it's thy extreame diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Yet now thy wondrous goodnes will not let mee,</l>
               <l>Diſpare of mercy for a world of paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thogh thou kill me, to thy hand I'le come,</l>
               <l>And thogh thou ſlay me, I ſhall ever loue thee,</l>
               <l>No chance no change ſhall ſo my ſpeech benume,</l>
               <l>But it ſhall praiſe thee as my thoghts do proue thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Touch, touch my lips, for oh my ſoule doth long</l>
               <l>To be annointed with thy heavenly grace,</l>
               <l>And thus I put a period to my ſong,</l>
               <l>Quhill I appeare before thy glorious face.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. George Muſchet Miniſter of the Evangell at Dunning.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20232:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
